<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of a mighty giant named Theutobocus, sometimes king of the Theutons and Cimbrians, overthrown by Consul Marius 1700 yeares agone buried then by the castle of Langon, neere the towne of Romans in the prouince of Daufiné in Fraunce, whole bones were found of by chaunce, an. 1613, in a place called to this day, The Giants Ground, and vpon his tombe ingrauen in old letters Theutobocus Rex.</title>
            <author>Tissot, Jacques.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24091.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2933</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29515023</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29515023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27991</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27991)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1859:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of a mighty giant named Theutobocus, sometimes king of the Theutons and Cimbrians, overthrown by Consul Marius 1700 yeares agone buried then by the castle of Langon, neere the towne of Romans in the prouince of Daufiné in Fraunce, whole bones were found of by chaunce, an. 1613, in a place called to this day, The Giants Ground, and vpon his tombe ingrauen in old letters Theutobocus Rex.</title>
                  <author>Tissot, Jacques.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Allde, dwelling neere Christ Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Jacques Tissot by STC (2nd Ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jugurthine War, 111-105 B.C.</term>
               <term>Giants --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Antiquities --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27991:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27991:1"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION OF A MIGHTY GIANT, named <hi>Theutobocus,</hi> ſomtimes King of the <hi>Theutons</hi> and Cimbrians, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne by Conſul <hi>Marius,</hi> 1700 yeares agone.</p>
            <p>Buried then by the Caſtle of <hi>Langon,</hi> neere the Towne of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in the Prouince of Daufine in <hi>Fraunce;</hi> Whoſe bones were found of by chaunce, An. 1613. in a place called to this day, <hi>The Giants ground;</hi> and vpon his Tombe in grauen in old letters <hi>Theutobocus Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q>IN DOMINO CONFIDO</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Edward Allde</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edoward Allde,</hi> dwelling neere Chriſt Church. 1615.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="relation">
            <pb facs="tcp:27991:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27991:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELATION OF THE GIANT THEVTOBOCVS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the many effects which this great mother and worke-miſtris <hi>Nature</hi> hath produced in this vnder-world, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue tallnes of Giants hath euer held one of the higheſt rancks vpon the Theater of wonders. Euen the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in ſondry places dtoh beare them witnes; And the hiſtoriographers in the deſcription of their ſo huge Colloſſes &amp; other relations, which the Poets in their Giganto-machies do ſhow the admiration wherein they were had. As alſo the very Etimology of their name doth inferr the ſame (for Giant ſignifieth a Son of the Earth) As though it were not of the nature &amp; poſſibility of men to be gett ſuch creatures. Hence the verſe Iuuenal. Sat. 4.</p>
            <q>Vnde fit vt malim fraterculus eſſe gigantum,</q>
            <p>Seemes to inferre an vncouth and extraordinary linage, as proceeding ſtraungely from the Earth.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27991:3"/>
which is alſo the cauſe that ſom who for their hie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes thought ſcorne to haue ſo low a birth, did boldy auouch that their Anceſtors were thoſe Angels, which the Greekes &amp; Latines call <hi>Demones</hi> and <hi>Genii:</hi> as if it <note place="margin">Lactant. Fir. lib. 10. cap. 15.</note> had ben impoſſible to Nature to haue brought forth ſuch high blood as they thought to be. Or that that great worke-miſtriſſe ſhould not haue bene able to haue imparted them, both an extreame heate &amp; moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture togither, the true cauſes of this exceſſiue tallnes; &amp; to bring this ſentence to effect,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Operatur natura quantum, &amp; quandiu poteſt, Ab extremis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Picolomin. de ſcientia ciuili gradu 10. c. 9. Ariſt. 9 de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura anima.</note> 
               <hi>ed extrema. Natura enim in ſuis operationibus non facit ſaltum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>It is moſt true then, that there haue ben Giants in this world, &amp; that they haue had men for their fathers, not only before, but alſo long after the floud. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from whence ſhould Goliath haue come? from whence Og King of Baſan? the firſt being 6. cubits &amp; a ſpanne high, &amp; the bed of the other 9. cubits long; the cubit according to the Greekes being 2. foote, &amp; to the Latines one foote &amp; a half, from whence all thoſe Amachins in reſpect of which the Iſraelits did ſeeme but as graſhoppers? And from whence all the reſt mentioned all along the Scriptures?</p>
            <p>Do not the fathers alſo &amp; almoſt al Hiſtoriographers teſtify with one conſent againſt all hard beleeuers, that in all ages, ſince at one time or other, there haue ben men of ſuch great &amp; extraordinary height?</p>
            <p>S. Auſten rehearſeth that a little before the Gothes affliction there was at Rome a woman-Giant whoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27991:3"/>
Parents did not exceede the common ſtature. <note place="margin">Plutarch in vita Sertorii. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Plutarch (the life &amp; ſoule of truth &amp; Antiquity) wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that Sertorius being entred the Towne of Tingis in Africk, and finding there a mighty, long and huge graue, where then Antheus told him that that famous Antheus of Libia was buried; a hard beleeuer, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, vpon meere incredulity cauſed it to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, where finding indeed a mans body full 30. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits long, with much wonder &amp; ſolemnity did ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto it peace-offrings, &amp; religiouſly cauſed it to be ſhutt againe.</p>
            <p>Pliny, moſt curious in the inquiry of naturall things, ſaith that in old Creta, now of later yeares called Candia, a great earthquake hauing turned vp a whole mountaine, there vnder was found a dead coarſe 46. cubits long, which ſome did auouch to be the body of Arion.</p>
            <p>Philoſtratus makes mention of 3. others of the ſame length, one of whoſe skulls he could not fill with 72. pints of Candia. Some others haue ſayd that one of them was 30. cubits high, the ſecond 22. &amp; the third 12. But becauſe he doth only deſcribe that which was found in the Iland of <hi>Cos</hi> which he ſaith was 18. foote long, not otherwiſe medling with that of Imbros, nor of Lemnos found by Menocrates, I am contented with the moſt verified things.</p>
            <p>Finally all hiſtorians make report of an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſuch other great bodies as of that of Oreſtes being 7. cubits long which was digged vp by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Oracle; That of whome there are yet ſome bones to be ſeen at Valence; As alſo of a liue woman, which Zonaras ſaith was a long cubit higher
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27991:4"/>
then any of the talleſt men of her time. And ſpecially of the Emperor Maximinus, which (as ſaith Iulius Capitolinus in his life, according to Codrus, did vſe his wiues bracelett as a ring to his finger; pulld and drew whole coaches &amp; carts loaden after him, broke &amp; bruyſed to duſt pouder a Topaſe between his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, eate at his meales 50. &amp; 60. pound of fleſh, dranke a certaine meaſure full, called <hi>Amphora Capitolina</hi> which is no leſſe then the eight part of an Hogſ-head; &amp; did wearie out 20. 25. &amp; 30. ſouldiers in wreſtling, &amp; beat downe to the ground ten of them at once, with many ſuch &amp; greater deedes that cannot but argue an extraordinary ſtrenght &amp; bignes.</p>
            <p>And if we will giue credit vnto Virgil in that great peece of ſtrength he doth attribute to Turnus in his combat againſt Aeneas, which yet is not likely he would haue fained to groſſely, but that he had either read, heard, or ſeen the like, you may ſee in the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes, that he alone pulld out of the ground a huge ſtone &amp; caſt it at his enemie, which hardly 12. other men could haue ſtirrd or lifted vp.</p>
            <p>I ſhould neuer end if I would go from time to time relating euery particular which is found in the ſtories, about Giants. One only, &amp; the ſame now in hand, (belonging to the King of France, which for ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cauſes he hath moſt graciouſly lent to the Printer &amp; bearer hereof) being now in England, is to be ſeen, as it hath ben already thorough moſt Proteſtant Countryes, for a preſent &amp; ready ey-witnes vnrepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable of what aboue we haue ſayd.</p>
            <p>The ſame bones Monſieur de Langon, (a worthy Gentleman of Daufine in France) found in a Tombe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27991:4"/>
which lay in a peece of ground of his, called to this day and of olde Giants-ground, where he had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of building, &amp; therfore of digging, where in by ſome Tombe was accompliſhed the Profery of Virgil,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gradiáque effoſsis mirabitur oſſa ſepulchris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tombe of theſe bones, 30. foote long was found ſome 17 or 18. foote deepe vnder the ground, hard by an old Caſtle in times paſt called <hi>Chaumont,</hi> now Langon, neere a little hillock; And the bones within were ſome putrified by reaſon of a certain ſlow ſpring which was found there, &amp; what bones ſoeuer the water or moiſture did touch, became as hard as ſtone, therfore as heauy. Some are yet naturally light and worme-eaten as commonly olde bones are. Some altogether periſht, and turned to duſt. But by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal peeces that are heere, which are no leſſe then 200. waight (the reſt being to heauy to carry eaſily vp and downe) the bones of the thigh and legg ſett toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being full 9. foote long, without neither the foot nor the ioint; wherby it may eaſily be perceiued, that (what ſoeuer the others were, either Orion of 46. foote, or Antheus of 30.) this our Giant could be no leſſe, at the very leaſt then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. foot high; Which yet doth ſuffice ouer &amp; aboue to rauiſh with admiration, ſuch as ſhall ſee thoſe limbs of his.</p>
            <p>For his teeth, whereas S. Auſten ſaith he ſaw one vpon the ſea ſhore at Vtica, which was a hundred times greater then any of our common ones; I thinke I may concurre to double that number in thoſe we haue 101. hands, to ſhow, whereupon euery body may imagine what an ouen he had for a mouth, what a gulfe for his belly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:27991:5"/>
And that I may not longer ſtand vpon euery peece we haue; whereof the beholders ſhal be more ſure &amp; content to truſt their owne eyes, then my deſcribing; Ile tell you but a word of the thicknes of his verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, wherby thoſe that haue euen any ſuperficiall skill in Anatomy may eaſily iudge the whole dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Giant, (according to the proportion of his legge and thigh aforeſaid) to haue ben aboue 25. foot, euery one of his vertebres being almoſt half a footlong, and the number of them in euery man 28. beſides thoſe 5. which are called <hi>diſsimilitudinary,</hi> whereupon I durſt almoſt ſay, he was very neere the whole length of the Tombe it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But that which is no leſſe to be noted then his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary height, is his owne name, ranck and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity thus found inſcribed vpon his Tombe, THEVTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BOCVS REX, for he indeed was a King or at leaſt one of the Kings, of that famous Army of Theutons, Tigurines, Ambruns and Cimbrians, which Marius defeated vpon the borders of Fraunce towards Italy, when they were ready to enter and inuade it, in the yeare of the foundation of Rome 642 and before the Incarnation of our Sauiour 105. For his name, quality and height <hi>Florus</hi> tells it vs in theſe few words lib. 3. cap. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Certe Rex ipſe Theutobocus quaternos, ſenoſque equos tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilire ſolitus, vix vnum cum f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>geret aſcendit, proximoque in ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> comprehenſus, inſigne ſpectaculum triumphi fuit, quippe vir proceritatis eximia ſuper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ropha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> opſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>manebat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King Theutobocus, who was wont to leape ouer 5. or 6. horſes, did ſcarce get vp vpon one, when he fled away; And ſo being taken in the next wood, was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27991:5"/>
a wonderfull ornament to the Triumph, for he being a man of an exceſſiue height, was higher then the very trophees for that warr. Oroſus lib. 5. cap. 16. doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe it a great deale more at length, and ſurely with a great deale more truth then any, ſaying that theſe Barbarians came with their huge Army to aſſayle Marius in his owne camp, neere the falling of the riuer Liſere into the Roſne, with whom hauing had ſome light skirmiſhes diuers dayes, at laſt thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtrong enough, they diuided their army in three, and ſo went three ſeuerall wayes; wherby Marius took time to diſlodge, and ſett his Campe in a place of more aduantage vpon a little hill, commaunding the enemies; from which falling to battell, he did kill 200000. of them and tooke 8000. priſoners; among the reſt making mencion of their king which either by error of report, or of former ſcribes, or late Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he calles Theutobodus, who (ſaith he) did make the victory more glorious by his death. As alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the very women, who ſeing they could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne from Marius, freedome for their bodies, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſerue their owne Gods according to their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, after they had killed, firſt their owne children, and then the moſt part one another, the reſt did hang themſelues at their cart-wheeles, ſome with ropes, ſome with their owne hayres.</p>
            <p>I know ſome will ſay with Plutarch and Florus that Marius did ouerthrow thoſe Barbariaus in another part of France hard by Aix, &amp; Marſeilles in a Prouince which is farr enough from Daufiné; And that the Marſilians did incloſe their vines with the bones of thoſe that were the ſlain, ſo great the diſcomfiture was.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27991:6"/>
But the anſwere is ready, that according to the huge numbers whereof this floud of men was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, Marius did not ouerthrow them all at once, by reaſon alſo that they had diuided themſelues, as Oro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaith; and that thoſe who were defeated there, we but the third part which went that way rowards I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, whome Marius alſo ouertooke and cut ſhort after he had ouerthrowen theſe former. And although Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus make but one of the ouerthrowes at Marſeilles and the death of Theutobocus; yet ſince he himſelfe doth ſpecifie the height of that king, and we finde him bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in this place, it muſt needes folow he was not kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led very farr thence. Finally though we had not thoſe ſtrong likelihoods and proofes we knowe that the firſt part of theſe Barbarians with their king Theutobocus were defeated not farre from the place where we haue found his Tombe, yet the modalls of the ſtamp hereunder repreſented, that haue ben found therein, marking ſo cleerely Marius, &amp; being ſo like to thoſe of the Amphitheator of Oranges, all which is alſo of Marius, do ſhow howſoeuer and proue without any difficulty, that this our Giant was none els then Theu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tobocus, a King among theſe Theutons, and other Barbarians, whom Conſul Marius ouerthrew vpon the borders of France either in Daufiné or Prouence, brought from whereſoeuer, and vpon what ſoeuer oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to be buried where we haue found him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="relation">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:27991:6"/>
            <head>A true Relation of the Bones of Giants, which are to be ſeene at this day, as well in <hi>Germany, Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Flanders, Holland, Frize, as in Italy, Lorraine, &amp; France.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By, I. B. G.</byline>
            <p>THe better to verifie that which we report, our <hi>Theutobocus</hi> of an Alma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de race, wee will ſpeake a word of the bones of Giants which are found at this day in Germany and elſewhere. Firſt in the Citty of <hi>Wornes,</hi> which is thought to be builded by the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, there is found the tombe of a Giant called <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusfephery</hi> or <hi>Iephem</hi> of the <hi>Horne,</hi> with a certain clouen ſtaffe and a ſtone wherewith he vſed to ſalute himſelfe; the which ſtaffe is as bigg as one could well brace in his armes as long as thirty ordinary paces, and the ſtone fower foote high large downwards ten paces &amp; vpward, before in the faſhion of a piramyd. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Town houſe there are many bones of diuers ſortes of diuers Beaſts very huge, as alſo diuers bones of men, as the broken bones of the arme and thigh of a Giant, which is of the bigneſſe of a foote round &amp; a foote and a halfe in length, and that of the thigh of the like bignes, but two foote and a halfe long.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Openhoin</hi> there is the whole bone of the thigh of a Giant three foote and a halfe long, and they ſay hee was borne in the ſame houſe where the bone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, the houſe is called vntill this day, the houſe of the Giant and is not ſolde without this bone.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Saint Troy</hi> there was found within the <hi>Rhine</hi> An. 1612. the bone of the left thigh of a Giant of the ſame
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27991:7"/>
bigneſſe that this of <hi>Theutobocus,</hi> foure foote long, the which is now at <hi>Cleues</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Monſieur Wiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> of the bones there were none but the inward part of the <note place="margin">Bocace ch. 68. 4 l. del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genealogie des Dieux.</note> skull beſides that of one thigh, yet not altogether whole but ſomewhat rotten. His teeth were waighed and three of them waighed 100 ounces. The ſame body was by skilfull men iudged to haue been 200 cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites. And thoſe teeth hang to this day with chaines in the Church of <hi>Drepano.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Hage</hi> hard by the wood there is a Gentleman who hath in his houſe a thigh bone 3 foote in hight, and in thicknes one.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Rotterdam</hi> algardener hath a legg bone two foote long, which he found in an Abbey. <note place="margin">Holland.</note>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Greninghen</hi> they holde it for true, of a Church there which hath beene builded by Giants without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Frize.</note> ladder. It is 25 foote in height, round aboue, after the forme of a Drum, and 40 foote in bredth; built vpon huge foure-ſquare pillars, and did ſerue for a kinde of houſe and ſtrong defence to them, 500 yeare before Chriſts comming.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Francfort</hi> there is a iaw tooth or grinder as they tearme them, as big as ones fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t which is in the handes of <hi>Monſieur Malepart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Darmeſtat</hi> there is in the houſe of the Prince ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bones of Giants.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Bona</hi> vpon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> there is to be ſeene a thigh bone of a Giant fiue foote high.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Ladebourg</hi> fiſhermen found the bodyes of two Giants the one 30 foote high, the other 22. who tooke away onely the thigh and legg bones of the greateſt.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Manom</hi> neere <hi>Frankendad,</hi> hath been found a hip
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27991:7"/>
bone of the bignes of the bullet of a battring Cannon.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Bartens</hi> hath a bigg bone of a mighty Giants thigh, which hath coſt him very deere; And hath beene ſhewed of late in <hi>Paris</hi> at the faire of S. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> being 3 foote and a halfe long.</p>
            <p>And in the time of <hi>Ceſar</hi> there liued a merueilous Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant called <hi>Druon,</hi> fifteene cubites high full of horrible and cruell tiranny, who liued in a very ſtrong Caſtle in <hi>Brabant</hi> ſcituate vpon a mariſhe by the ſide of the riuer <hi>Schaldis;</hi> the which Giant conſtrained all that paſt that riuer to leaue there the moyetie of their marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dizes, and if any did faile all was forfeited, and the Marchant loſt his hand. Wherefore the place was named <hi>Hant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp,</hi> which is as much to ſay; as cut off the hand, which is now called <hi>Anwerp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With this Giant fought a Knight of Caeſars called <hi>Brarius</hi> and brauely ſlew him, whence it is likely that the word, braue came Thoſe of the towne of <hi>Anwerpe</hi> ſhow at this day in their town-houſe ſome bones of the ſaid Giant, which are of marueilous greatnes.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Bruges</hi> in the Priſon of the towne vnder the gate vppon two Irons, there is a thigh-bone bigg in the middeſt, of a foote in roundnes, and long three foote and a halfe, and is ſaid to be of a Giant which builded the priſon without a ladder.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Stenan</hi> in digging the ditches of the Towne hath been found the whole bones of a Giant 22 foote high in the time that the Duke of <hi>Butkion</hi> held it, from the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two yeares ſince there was found within 3 leagues of <hi>Mets</hi> the head of a Giant which was as bigg as the barrel of a drum, which was returned to the ſaid Duke,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27991:8"/>
ſauing three teeth which ſome ſpeciall Burgeſſes of that Citty keepe to themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bocace</hi> affirmeth that in his time in the bottome of a mountain neare the citty of <hi>Drepan</hi> in <hi>Scicily</hi> was found the whole Body of a marueilous Giant, in his full pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion holding a ſtaffe club, or rather a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee of the forme of a maſt of a ſhip, the which ſtaffe being touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, went preſently to duſt, being garniſhed within with leade, which being melted weighed fifteen quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, euery quintal containing a hundred pound. The Body being likewiſe touched turned to duſt, except ſome bones and three of his teeth.</p>
            <p>In the Caſtle of <hi>Moulins</hi> in the prouince of <hi>Bourthere</hi> is the Picture of an huge bon'd Giant, with a true <note place="margin">France<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> ſhoulder bone of his, which might well ſerue for a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſix men.</p>
            <p>All which thinges are yet, either to be ſeene to this day, or read in faithfull Authors: therefore without doubt ſo true, as they that will gaine ſay them, muſt needes be euen leſſe then Pigmies in any skill, witt, learning, or iudgement, and more then very Giants in ignorance, rudeneſſe and brutiſhneſſe.</p>
            <q>Admire and praiſe God for his mighty and wondrous workes in Heauen and Earth.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27991:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27991:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27991:9"/>
            <trailer>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of man</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
